בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is נ"ח, Nun Chet,
58, and we're in the middle of some really central discussions for
practical הלכה Halacha in terms of—the first issue was when does the
wine become wine? When it gets into the vat, once it starts
drawing away from the grapes, even if, you know, whole discussion as
I mentioned about, let's say, it even puddles within the cask, which
is a discussion תוספות Tosfos had. But now we get to something
which is a much bigger and more practical issue, and that's why
there's these large תוספותים Tosfosim and the דפים dapim are relatively short,
is what type of touch makes it forbidden?
Direct, indirect, with intent, not with intent, and so on. And what
degree of forbidden? Forbidden to drink, forbidden to get הנאה, hana'ah, etc.
So the גמרא Gemara two days ago ended with a whole discussion
about stomping with the legs without touching with the hands. And,
but yesterday, there was a very critical discussion, and again, part of
the issue is exactly how you explain what the parameters are. The
גמרא Gemara started with the discussion of a
non-Jew coming down from a tree holding a לולב lulav essentially, a
palm branch, and unintentionally touching the wine with the tip of the
palm branch. Now that actually is a combination of two factors. The
two reasons for leniency there: one is it's indirect, and the second
is it was without intention. But then as the גמרא Gemara continued
its discussion yesterday, it talked about the case about like an infant,
a תינוק, tinok, or, you know, a small child who touches without
intent. And there, presumably, it's a case of direct touch; it might
lack intent, but at least it's a case of direct touch. And
then it ended similarly with a non-Jew who came into a store
and was upset that the Jew wasn't selling him the wine and
stuck his hand in the wine as if, "What's this? Isn't this
wine?" And then that also was an issue about that, and that
was also a case of direct touch and also without intent. Now
even without intent, we have to explain—I mean, he intended to touch
it, so without intent there sort of means like without clearly the
context was there was no intent in order to maybe use it
in an עבודה זרה avodah zarah context or something of that nature.
But it did shift from indirect touch without intent to direct touch
without intent. So let me just summarize the basic conclusion of that.
תוספות Tosfos in a very long תוספות Tosfos on yesterday's דף daf
basically says that the case of the guy coming down from the
palm tree was not that he touched it indirectly; it was that
he touched it directly. He has a different version of the text
in the גמרא. Gemara. And he says if he actually did touch
it indirectly and it was the combination of indirect and without intent,
then everybody would agree that the wine would be totally permissible. And
this becomes actually an important principle which we should start actually making
a chart. Okay, this actually becomes an important principle of,
you know, when you have these two factors combined, okay.
I have to figure out what the chart is going to be.
Okay, but anyway,
let me think how to do this in a chart. Okay,
but
anyway,
I don't even know, I'm just going to write it for myself,
I'll figure out how to synthesize it as a chart later, but
anyway, if it's indirect
plus no intent
touch, there's always a question of intent to what, so this is
even okay, then the הלכה Halacha is you can even drink it,
even
drink, totally okay. That's how תוספות. Tosfos. תוספות Tosfos says that the
discussion in the גמרא Gemara was where it was direct touch, but
if it genuinely was the combination of the two, it would be
totally okay. So if you look at תוספות Tosfos on the bottom
on נ"ז ע"א, Nun Zayin Amud Aleph, I'll just read you the
one punchline there at the bottom, this big תוספות Tosfos הכי גרסינן,
Hachi Garsinan, so at the end of that תוספות, Tosfos, he says,
he says like this.
Okay, hold on,
I'm sorry, let me just try to find the line,
he
says... okay, if you just look at the very bottom, he says
like this. אלא והא כאן
נגע ביה, Ela ve-ha kan naga bei, four lines above the new
תוספות Tosfos תינוק, Tinok, he says, אבל אם היה נוגע ביין על
ידי נטלא, Aval im haya nogea be-yayin al yedei natla, נטלא natla
is like a cup, מזה אינו חושש דשרי אפילו בשתייה. mizeh eino
choshesh de-shari afilu be-shtiya. Alright. וכן פסק רבינו תם הלכה למעשה ve-chen
pasak Rabbeinu Tam halacha le-ma'aseh the very last line of the תוספות
Tosafot דמגע עובד כוכבים de-maga oved kochavim על ידי דבר אחר al
yedei davar acher שלא בכוונת מגע she-lo be-chavanat maga מותר בשתייה. mutar
bishtiyah. Okay,
so the combination of these two,
indirect and no intent to touch, if it's totally okay even to
drink. All right, so that is what תוספות Tosafot says, and therefore
he says the story that you thought was the basis of the
discussion yesterday
was like not the right version of the story. If it really
was the combination of the two, indirect and not intent to touch,
it would be totally permissible even to drink. Okay, and therefore תוספות
Tosafot actually says the discussion really yesterday was about a case where
it was not intent to touch but it was direct. Okay, and
then that was the שמועה shmu'ah about the case of the infant.
Now, what is the conclusion about the case of the infant? Let's
talk about that for a moment, or the small child. The גמרא
Gemara says the infant means that he doesn't know the nature
of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So there was a debate, right? According
to one version, okay,
רב's Rav position was that it was that a תינוק tinok makes
something into סתם יינם. stam yeinam. Now the גמרא Gemara modified it
to say that he meant that it made it forbidden to drink,
not forbidden to get הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, but yes, the touch of
a תינוק tinok makes it at least forbidden to drink. שמואל, Shmuel,
right? If you remember, there was a whole discussion about this ברייתא
braita about a slave and, you know, an adult, a child. Does
he still talk about עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, not talk about עבודה
זרה? avodah zarah? So the way שמואל Shmuel read that ברייתא braita
was that a touch of a child actually he rejected רב. Rav.
It's permissible to drink. So which way do we rule about that?
By the way, a related ruling was if you remember שמואל Shmuel
also introduced a new idea. And שמואל's Shmuel idea was was that
if a slave converts, it still is a problem of making סתם
יינם stam yeinam as long for a year, as long as he's
still talking about the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So that also became
an interesting question that תוספות Tosafot asks, which is if practically they
owned slaves, you know, and they said do our slaves still make
things סתם יינם, stam yeinam, does it for a full year or
not? Okay, so what is the story with that? So that was
another related practical question. So the beginning of this big תוספות Tosafot
here on נ"ז עמוד ב' לאפוקי nun zayin amud bet la'apukei first
brings all the evidence that indicates that we rule like שמואל, Shmuel,
both to be strict that when you buy a slave or whatever,
even after he converts it takes a full year. By the way,
תוספות Tosafot says that's only about a slave, right, because if somebody
just converts freely, then obviously when they get to that stage of
converting then they've hopefully, if you're doing it right, are no longer
talking about their past religion. Okay, but if somebody is a slave,
he says even if technically speaking, this is a very interesting תוספות
Tosafot about the idea about coercive power, תוספות Tosafot says even if
technically speaking the slave is freely agreeing to convert, he's not really
freely agreeing to convert. He's agreeing to convert because that's his owner
is pressuring him and the circumstances are pressuring him. So a slave
would convert without fully having abandoned their previous faith. Okay, but anyway,
תוספות Tosafot says so תוספות Tosafot first brings the evidence that we
rule like שמואל, Shmuel, that if you buy a slave you have
to wait a year, and on the flip side if a קטן
katan touches something, then that actually would be totally okay, all right,
even to drink. That's שמואל's Shmuel position. And then תוספות Tosafot adds
to that, and this becomes really critical
for the ראשונים, Rishonim, the idea that nowadays, remember what is the
definition of a minor in the discussion yesterday? Does anybody remember? Was
it given by age, by years? No, even a בן יומו, ben
yomo, but somebody is still a minor until like they are לא
ידעי בטיב עבודה זרה. lo yadei be-tiv avodah zarah. They don't really
understand the whole nature of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So תוספות Tosafot
makes an assertion that since our non-Jews, the Christians he's talking about,
don't really do libations for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It's interesting because
they still drink the wine in the Eucharist. Okay,
and but that's what the priest is doing. Let's talk about your
standard non-Jew are not using it in that type of a ritual
way and they don't do libations. He says all of our non-Jews
nowadays are like the תינוק. tinok. They don't know about עבודה זרה
avodah zarah in the sense of not that he, you know, he
still believed Christianity was עבודה זרה avodah zarah as we've been seeing
throughout the מסכת, masechet, but they don't actually, they're not part of
the whole discourse or the whole context of using wine in a
type of a libation and a type of, certainly the laity is
not. So therefore תוספות Tosafot wanted to say they're like an infant.
Well, if you say that, you would come to the conclusion, okay,
so you said that we rule like שמואל, Shmuel, that an infant
doesn't make it a problem and you can even drink it, and
our non-Jews are like these infants in the sense of that they're
out of the category of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So therefore it
should be מותר mutar to even drink the wine of non-Jews. Yep.
And he really comes to that possibility, maybe we could just סתם
stam drink the wine. Goodbye the... everything we're learning. I've been arguing
this for years. Okay, well anyway, so תוספות, Tosafos, if you take
a look, if you take a look at the middle of the
תוספות, Tosafos, לאפוקי מדרב, la'afukei mi'derav, תוספות Tosafos says, you see there's
a little ד dalet in parentheses about 15 lines down. Okay, the
line starts with the words כוכבים בחובותינו. Kochavim Bechovoseinu. Okay, so first
he says, I might maybe we'll start one line above that. He
says like this. He says, or if you go two lines above
that, he says, ועוד פירש רשב"ם וריב"ן בשם רש"י. ve'od peirush Rashbam
ve'Riban beshem Rashi. You see the word רש"י Rashi at the end
of a line, about 15 lines down from that תוספות. Tosafos. He
says they say in the name of רש"י Rashi שכתב בתשובת הגאונים.
shekasav b'teshuvas ha'Geonim. Line starts with the words שכתב בתשובת הגאונים. shekasav
b'teshuvas ha'Geonim. שבזמן הזה אין איסור הנאה במגע עובדי כוכבים. shebazman hazeh
ein issur hana'ah bemaga ovdei kochavim. Nowadays when non-Jews, the Christians, touch
wine, there's no prohibition of הנאה, hana'ah, which is critical, which means
that we can do business with it. We might not drink it,
we could do business. ביין כי עובדי כוכבים של עכשיו אין רגילים
לנסך לעבודת כוכבים. beyayin ki ovdei kochavim shel achshav ein regilim lenasech
l'avodas kochavim. They don't use the wine for עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
וחשובים כאינם יודעים בטיב עבודת כוכבים. vechashuvim k'einam yodim betiv avodas kochavim.
It's like they don't know about it, which is our definition in
the גמרא Gemara about a תינוק. tinok.
ומשמשא והוו להו כתינוק בן יומו. umeshamsha ve'havu lehu k'tinok ben yomo.
Okay, ועל זה אנו סומכים לגבות יינם של עובדי כוכבים בחובותינו. ve'al
zeh anu somchim ligbos yeinam shel ovdei kochavim bechovoseinu. That's why when
a non-Jew doesn't pay up their debts, we can seize their wine
and resell it, and therefore it's not a problem of deriving benefit.
So it was very practical in terms of being able to use
it also like in the money lending context, to be able to
use it to collect from, okay, if you treat them like an
infant. But then he says, one minute, but let's take that to
its logical conclusion. If you treat them like an infant, it shouldn't
be permissible not only in terms of benefit, but to drink. So
that's the next line. He says, ועל דבר זה שלח לו ר"י
לרבינו תם. ve'al davar zeh shalach lo Ri l'Rabbeinu Tam. ר"י, Ri,
which is רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam nephew, sent to רבינו תם. Rabbeinu
Tam.
דחזי, dechazi, he says, it appears דמינך, deminach, based on your ruling,
ומאבוך, ume'avuch, and your father's ruling, meaning your grandfather's ruling, who was
רש"י, Rashi, okay, ומאחוך, ume'achuch, and your brother's ruling, who was רבינו
תם's Rabbeinu Tam brother. Anybody? רשב"ם. Rashbam. The רשב"ם. Rashbam. Okay, משתרי
מגע עובדי כוכבים ביין לעלמא אפילו בשתייה. mishtarei maga ovdei kochavim beyayin
l'alma afilu b'shtiyah. From what you've been saying, you should be able
to even drink the wine of non-Jews. דאחיך רבינו שמואל, de'achich Rabbeinu
Shmuel, the רשב"ם, Rashbam, פסק בשם אבוך, pasak beshem avuch, ruled in
the name of your father, meaning your grandfather, רבינו שלמה, Rabbeinu Shlomo,
רש"י, Rashi, דעובדי כוכבים בזמן הזה אינם חשובים אלא כתינוק בן יומו,
de'ovdei kochavim bazman hazeh einam chashuvim ela k'tinok ben yomo, that we
treat non-Jews nowadays who don't use wine for this purpose like this
infant, okay, and therefore, what's the ruling of that? ואתה פוסק, ve'atah
posek, and you, רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, rule, let's combine it. I
know how to add one plus one, because you and רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam rule בתינוק בן יומו כשמואל דאית ליה דאינו עושה יין
נסך לאסור אף בשתייה. betinok ben yomo k'Shmuel d'is leh d'eino oseh
yayin nesech le'esor af b'shtiyah. If you rule like שמואל, Shmuel, you
don't it's if an infant touches it, it's not even forbidden to
drink. So we should be able to drink it. So here's where
חיים סולובייצ'יק Chaim Soloveitchik said if the ראשונים Rishonim had wanted to,
they could have wiped away all of the laws of יין נסך
yayin nesech by making this argument. But somehow there was too deep
of a taboo around this. You know, they had to either because
of the גמרא Gemara or because practically, like with their loaning, they
had to be able to take the wine and resell it, and
they had to find these like leniencies. But there was a sense
like you can't go that far. You can't really make it permissible,
right? There was still this deep taboo around it. So that was
like an inconceivable conclusion. It was almost like they didn't want to
get that far. They didn't want to get to that conclusion. But
here's his point. Why not just allow it completely? והשיב לו רבינו
תם, ve'heshiv lo Rabbeinu Tam, so רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam responded to
him, כי הכותב שכתב נבהל היה לפסוק. ki hachosev shekasav nivhal hayah
lifsok.
The one who wrote in my name that the wine of a
תינוק tinok would be permissible of an infant even to drink, he
was overeager. I didn't say that. חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, like it's
so funny we had this once before, God forbid, like if remember
we should rule like a certain position, that was about the issue
about like עבודה זרה avoda zara in private. Anyway, here it says
וחס ושלום שלא עלה לבו אלא ודאי קיימא לן כרב באיסור לגבי
שמואל ותינוק בן יומו עושה יין נסך לאסור אף בשתייה. vechas v'shalom
shelo alah libo ela vadai kaima lan k'Rav b'issur legabe Shmuel v'tinok
ben yomo oseh yayin nesech le'esor af b'shtiyah.
God forbid. We don't rule like שמואל, Shmuel, we rule like רב.
Rav. Even if it was touched by an infant, it would still
be forbidden to drink. All we're saying is yes, they're like infants,
etc., okay, but even so, all we're saying is is that it's
permissible to get benefit. We're not saying it's permissible to drink because
we actually rule like רב Rav that it's forbidden to drink. And
by the way, the related thing is that also that leniency, because
if they come together, it means that when we buy a slave,
it's not a problem even immediately. We don't have to wait the
year, right? That was the other part of the equation yesterday. So
here's a key line in תוספות Tosafos where he actually could have
concluded that there's no problem of wine if we combined the rulings
the right way, but in the end he rules actually that it
is a problem to drink, it's just not a problem to derive
benefit. And at the very end of תוספות, Tosafos, he actually explains
a logic behind this, because then he works in the whole question,
how do we do this like, aren't we changing the תקנה, takanah,
etc., etc., and he actually says a very good logic, and here's
his logic. He says, listen, I'm paraphrasing. Obviously, there are two reasons
why we don't drink the wine of non-Jews. What are the two
reasons why we don't drink the wine of non-Jews? נסך. nesech.
עבודה זרה avoda zara and socialization leading to intermarriage and so on.
So תוספות Tosafot says oh so if it's true that our non-Jews
I mean maybe they're still over there עבודה זרה avoda zara but
in תוספות Tosafot's mind but they don't use the wine in this
context that removes the עבודה זרה avoda zara context. But what but
what does it not remove? Concerns of socializing and intermarriage. So that
leads to a perfect conclusion which is don't drink their wine but
you can get benefit. So you know besides fitting it into the
תינוק tinok category and technically it's מגע שלא בכוונה maga shelo bekavana
touching without intent like that's all very nice but also categorically as
you know in terms of if we think about the people we're
interacting with we don't really you know as you know not just
oh in this one case he touched it without intent like that's
not the point. The point more is the non-Jews we're dealing with
there's not really this עבודה זרה avoda zara concern related to wine
but there is an intermarriage concern and therefore the logical conclusion
is you can't drink it but you can get benefit. So let's
take a look at that at the very end of this תוספות.
Tosafot. He says
okay it's ואם תאמר ve-im tomar it's about seven lines from the
bottom near the end of the line. ואם תאמר ve-im tomar if
you
say כיון דגזרו על ניסוך עובדי כוכבים הוי ליה דבר שבמנין דצריך
מנין אחר להתירו keivan de-gazru al nisuch ovdei kochavim havei lei davar
she-biminyan de-tzarich minyan acher le-hattiro so how do we say that oh
you know well in our case it only applies to drinking and
not to get הנאה? hana'ah? ויש לומר דלא גזרו אלא על המנסכים
ve-yesh lomar delo gazru ela al ha-menaschim they only made the גזירה
gezeira on those types of non-Jews that use wine do libations in
their עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay. וכיון דהשתא לא הוי מנסכים לעבודת
כוכבים ve-keivan de-hashta lo havei menaschim l'avodat kochavim so now he's approaching
it not from the תינוק tinok perspective but from the nature of
the non-Jews we're dealing with you know in a more global way.
This idea that there's an איסור issur of deriving benefit is non-Jews
who use it in libation contexts. But non-Jews who don't use it
in libation
contexts יש לתלות להיתר yesh litlos le-heter you can be lenient. וראיה
לדבר מדאמרינן דרבא שדר קרבנא לבר ששך ביומי דאידם ve-raya la-davar mid-amrinan
de-Rava shadar qorbana le-Bar Sheshach be-yomei de-idim remember the idea of doing
business on their holiday? So he sent a gift to this non-Jew
on his holiday. אמר קים לי בגוויה דלא פלח לעבודת כוכבים amar
kim li be-gaveih de-lo palach l'avodat kochavim I know he doesn't worship
idols. ואף על גב דגמרא משא ומתן ביום אידם הוי דבר שבמנין
ve-af al gav de-gam masa u-mattan be-yom eidam havei davar she-biminyan but
doing business on their holidays was also a rabbinic enactment ולא הוצרך
מנין אחר להתירו ve-lo hutzrach minyan acher le-hattiro why didn't he say
oh you needed it to be formally revoked? אלא דלהנהו דלא עבדו
מודו כברייתא מתחלה לא גזרו עלייהו ela de-le-hanhu de-lo avdu modu ke-varaita
mi-tchila lo gazru aleihu but no for non-Jews who never were in
the category of celebrating the
holidays okay the גזירה gezeira never applied to those non-Jews who didn't
celebrate the holidays. Similarly here the idea never applied to those non-Jews
who don't use it in libations. But then תוספות Tosafot says one
minute מיהו קשיא סתם יינם היך נתיר בהנאה כיון דגזרו אסתם יינם
משום בנותיהם mihu kashya stam yeinam heich nattir be-hana'ah keivan de-gazru a-stam
yeinam mishum benoteihem but one minute what about the problem of intermarriage?
Okay maybe there's no עבודה זרה avoda zara problem what about the
intermarriage problem? וגם עתה שייך זה הטעם ve-gam ata shayach zeh ha-ta'am
nowadays it's also an intermarriage concern. ויש לומר דמאי דגזרו סתם יינם
לאסור בהנאה יותר מפתם ושמנם ve-yesh lomar de-mai de-gazru stam yeinam le-esor
be-hana'ah yoter mi-pittam ve-shamnam why is wine forbidden in benefit and their
bread and their oil and their other stuff is permissible in benefit
just forbidden to eat right? משום דשכיחי לניסוך לעבודה זרה mishum de-shchichi
le-nisuch l'avoda zara the extra stringency of wine is associated with עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. But right that's why it's weightier. אבל עתה שבטל
ניסוך שאינם יודעים בטיב עבודת כוכבים aval ata she-bittul nisuch she-einam yode'im
be-tiv avodat kochavim now that they don't use it for libations so
okay it doesn't have the stringencies of wine but it goes into
the normal category of things of non-Jews we don't eat in order
not to lead to intermarriage.
Okay? דייו להיות כפתם ושמנם או כבישולי עובדי כוכבים לאסור בשתייה ולא
בהנאה dayo lihyot ke-pittam ve-shamnam o ke-bishulei ovdei kochavim le-esor bi-shtiya velo
be-hana'ah that you can't drink it but you can get benefit. והמחמיר
תבא עליו ברכה. ve-ha-machmir tavo alav beracha. So this big תוספות Tosafot
of yesterday which is why yesterday's דף daf was shorter okay today's
דף daf will also be short basically discusses what's the story nowadays
with Christians and wine. And his basic conclusion is he could have
come to a conclusion that you can even drink it because they
don't use it for עבודה זרה avoda zara they're like a תינוק
tinok and תינוק tinok is even allowed to drink etcetera. That was
too radical okay and in the end he comes to a conclusion
that you can basically you can't drink I'm sorry I said it
he could have yeah you could have come to a conclusion you
can even drink it but in the end he comes to a
conclusion don't drink it but you can get benefit. So you can
do business with it you can seize it in debt but don't
but don't drink it by nicely splitting between the עבודה זרה avoda
zara element and the intermarriage element. So because the עבודה זרה avoda
zara element isn't so relevant they don't really use it in that
context even though he's saying that they're still עובדי עבודה זרה ovdei
avoda zara okay it's you can get benefit. That's but intermarriage is
still an issue so don't drink it. And the other way is
like fitting it into this תינוק tinok type of a case. Yes.
Did any of the Sefardic ראשונים Rishonim discuss these issues? I am
sure that they did but I do not have an answer off
the top of my head of exactly how they construed it.
Right. Exactly. Okay. So yeah. Do you ever consider using it doesn't
sound good but using עבדים avadim For like express גיור? giyur?
For what? Express גיור? giyur? Yeah, I mean that does come up
a little bit, the whole עבד eved issues around it. Right, right,
right. I mean, yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah, there is that is brought
up in some discussions. Okay, so now let's pick up... I'm going
to... I know it was read yesterday but I want to just
pick it up for my sake. So we have two things now.
One is the case about the לולב Lulav saying that that was
the wrong גרסא girsa and actually indirect plus no intent is totally
okay even to drink. That was the first thing. The second thing
is the case about the תינוק, tinok, okay, or
not knowing about עבודה זרה avoda zara and wine, you know, which
for תוספות Tosafos becomes the case about, you know, about, for תוספות
Tosafos becomes Christians of
his day.
Okay, so in that case, there were two possibilities. One is don't
drink...
I'm sorry, drink... no...
don't drink plus get
הנאה, hana'ah, and the other possibility was you can even drink it,
and that would have been too drastic, so תוספות Tosafos basically says
no, no, no, you can't drink it, that would have been... that's
שמואל's Shmuel idea, okay, he basically rules like this, don't drink and
get הנאה, hana'ah, and that becomes very relevant for that. Okay, and
the other sort of related explanation of that is what do you
call it, is that it's no עבודה זרה avoda zara concern,
yes intermarriage concern.
So שמואל's Shmuel not
concern... This was שמואל Shmuel and this was רב. Rav.
שמואל's Shmuel not concerned with intermarriage? Well, שמואל Shmuel was talking about
a תינוק. tinok. תוספות Tosafos is extending it to a גדול. gadol.
By a תינוק, tinok, there's really not an intermarriage concern. Okay, but
because תוספות Tosafos wants to extend it to Christians of his day,
okay, so here it's okay, here you can even drink,
okay, here don't drink but you can get הנאה. hana'ah. All right,
now, third case, which is ours, which is going to be direct
touch, no כוונה. kavanah. And the question is no כוונה kavanah for
what?
Direct touch
plus no
כוונה. kavanah. That's the case that we ended with yesterday. All right,
so let's pick that up at the bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב'.
Nun-Zayin Amud Beis. I'm going to re-read this. Okay.
Okay, ההוא עובדא, hahu uvda, one, two, three, four, five, and eight
lines from the bottom, or nine lines from the bottom. ההוא עובדא
דהוה במחוזא, hahu uvda dehavah bemechuza, a story in מחוזא. Mechuza. עובד
כוכבים אתא ו...... Akum ata ve'idkallek... an- no, עובד כוכבים אתא ואנח
ליה, Akum ata ve'anach leh, a non-Jew came, עייל לחנותא דישראל, ayel
lachanusa deyisrael, came into the store of a Jew. אמר להו אית
לכו חמרא? Amar lehu is lachu chamra? Do you have wine? לזבוני?
Lizvunei? To sell? אמרו ליה לא. Ameru leh lo. No. הוה יתיב
חמרא בדבלא, Hava yasiv chamra bedavla, so there was wine there in
a like in a in a in a pail. שדא ביה ידא,
Shada be yad, so he stuck his hand in it, ושישכא ביה,
shishey beih, moved his hand around. Okay, and moving your hand around
is always a bigger concern about יין נסך yayin nesech than just
touching it. אמר להו האי לאו חמרא הוא? Amar lehu hai lav
chamra hu? What? This isn't wine? שקליה ההוא ביריתחיה, Shaklei hech beris-chei,
so the Jew now took it, got very angry, שדייה לדנא, shadi
le danna, and
says get your hand out of there and threw it into the
main barrel. Now you got a problem. The non-Jew touched the wine,
made it forbidden, now that wine got mixed up in the main
barrel. Okay, so שדייה לדנא. shadi le danna. שרא רבא לזבוניה לעובדי
כוכבים. Sharei Rava lizvunei le-ovdei kochavim. רבא Rava said okay, not a
problem, maybe it's forbidden in שתייה, shtiya, but you can still sell
it to a non-Jew. Okay. איפליגי בה רב הונא בר חיננא ורב
הונא בריה דרב נחמן. Iflegei lei Rav Huna bar Chinena ve-Rav Huna
brei de-Rav Nachman. רב הונא Rav Huna and רב חיננא Rav Chinena
disagreed with him. נפק שיפורא דרבא ושרא, Nafak shipura de-Rava ve-sharei, the
שופר shofar like the announcement of רבא Rava came out and said
it's permissible, ונפק שיפורא דרב הונא בר חיננא ורב הונא בריה דרב
נחמן ואסרי, ve-nafak shipura de-Rav Huna bar Chinena ve-Rav Huna brei de-Rav
Nachman va-asiri, and their announcement came out that it's forbidden. Okay, so
that's the issue here. Now, איקלע רב הונא בריה דרב נחמן למחוזא.
itkala Rav Huna brei de-Rav Nachman le-Mechuza. רב הונא, Rav Huna, the
son of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, who was one of the ones
who made it forbidden, came to מחוזא. Mechuza. Now I'm going to
read this story, I don't know how Dan read it yesterday, but
I'm going to read it like תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos reads the
following story differently than רש"י. Rashi. Okay, now רב הונא Rav Huna
was רבא's Rava רבי Rebbe actually, מחוזא Mechuza was where רבא Rava
lived. So רבא Rava said it was permissible and רב הונא Rav
Huna his רבי Rebbe said it was forbidden. So then רב הונא
Rav Huna came to רבא's Rava city. To רבא's, Rava so, אמר
ליה רבא לרב אליקים, amar lei Rava le-Rav Elyakim, so רבא Rava
said to רב אליקים Rav Elyakim שמעיה, shamayei, his attendant, טרוק טרוק
גלי, tarok tarok gali, go shut the door, דלא ניתי איניש דניטרד,
delo neisei inish denitred, that nobody should come and interfere with us.
Now the way רש"י Rashi reads it is close the door and
don't let רב הונא Rav Huna in here, he's going to give
me a hard time. But תוספות Tosafos says no, that doesn't work
basically the grammar doesn't work in how it'd tell the story, and
anyway really? How could you think that רבא Rava wouldn't want to
have a discussion about his position, like what type of a... Rabbi,
you know, he says רבא Rava anyway, he says even if you
want to say some Rabbis maybe were like that, he says we
know from other stories רבא Rava was always ready to concede when
he made a mistake, et cetera. So תוספות Tosafos doesn't read it
that way. תוספות Tosafos says what it means is, he said look,
I need some private time with רב הונא, Rav Huna, with my
רבי, Rebbe, shut the door and make sure nobody else disturbs us
when I'm talking to my רבי Rebbe רב הונא. Rav Huna. So
that's the way תוספות Tosafos reads it, very different from רש"י. Rashi.
Okay, על
גבי, al gabei,
so רבא Rava went to רב הונא. Rav Huna. Okay, that's the
way תוספות Tosafos reads it. אמר ליה כי האי גוונא מאי, amar
lei ki hai gavna mai, he said to רב הונא, Rav Huna,
he said look, this was the case, the case was this guy
came, he moved his hand around, blah blah blah, I heard you
said it's forbidden, but like what is the הלכה? halacha? So אמר
ליה אסור אפילו בהנאה. amar lei assur afilu bahana'ah. So he said
what we read on the previous עמוד. amud. רב הונא Rav Huna
said to him yeah, it's forbidden. So then רבא Rava said to
רב הונא, Rav Huna, ואמר הוא דאמר שכשוכך אינו עושה יין נסך?
ve'amar hu de'amar shichshuch eino ose yain nesech? How could you say
that? When I ruled it was permissible, I was ruling based on
the tradition I received from you. And the tradition I received from
you was, you said that if a non-Jew moves his hand in
it, and again is not סתם stam moves his hand in it,
that's classic יין נסך, yain nesech, but moves his hand in this
type of a scenario where it's clearly done like at a fit
of anger, you know, it's not done in some context that we
have to be concerned that he was using it in an עבודה
זרה avoda zara context, it's clearly a type of a fit of
anger, didn't isn't it your rule, didn't you say that it's not
a problem? So אמר, amar, so רב הונא Rav Huna said back
to him, אימר דאמרי, eimar de'amri, when did I say it's not
a problem, אנא לבר מדמי. ana lebar midmei. I meant that if
in the case like yours that you were dealing with where he
touched the wine, the wine is a problem, but what it meant
is if that wine got mixed up with other wine, okay, then
you can sell the whole barrel minus the added wine. So if
in this barrel there was 99 units of fine wine, of wine
that had not been disturbed, this one unit the non-Jew moved his
hand in, said רב הונא, Rav Huna, I would say that unit
is forbidden. Now you take that unit and you throw it in
the barrel, okay, so now, you know, it's a mixture, wine in
wine,
the whole thing is forbidden, you can't get הנאה, hana'ah, but what
you really just can't get הנאה hana'ah is from that one unit.
So if you sell this barrel for 99 dollars, assuming it goes
at a dollar a unit, you're fine. You only sold the 99
units that were permissible and you didn't you didn't sell the one
unit that was forbidden, that you threw in for free as it
were. You get it? So that's why if a little gets mixed
up, even if it's not בטל battel and it's אסור בהנאה, assur
behana'ah, it doesn't make the other wine אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, it
just means there's some wine in here that's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah.
So sell the whole thing minus the cost of the wine that's
mixed up. So he said when I said it was you could
sell it, I meant sell it in that context, I didn't mean
you could sell it for its full value. So says רב נחמן
Rav Nachman to רבא, Rava, again this is the way תוספות Tosafos
reads this, you רבא Rava misunderstood me. You said it was totally
permissible, I never said that. I said that in this type of
a context it's forbidden. Okay, ההוא חמרא דמאי, hadahu chamra demai, okay,
אמר ליה אימר דאמרי אנא, amar lei eimar de'amri ana, when did
I say it, לבר מדמי דההוא חמרא, lebar midmei dehu chamra, if
you didn't charge the the cost of that wine. דמי דההוא חמרא
מי אמרי? demai dehu chamra mi amri? I never said that actually
you could sell the wine itself that got forbidden, I didn't say
that wine was forbidden. אמר רבא, amar Rava, so said רבא, Rava,
כי אתאי לפומבדיתא, ki asai le'Pumbedisa, okay, so רבא Rava now heard
that his רבי Rebbe actually taught him otherwise than he did, maybe
he had misunderstood his רבי, Rebbe, whatever, it's not yet clear he
reversed himself. But now another story's going to happen that's going to
lead him to reverse himself or to see that he was really
wrong. כי אתאי לפומבדיתא ki asai le'Pumbedisa when I went to פומבדיתא,
Pumbedisa, which is where אביי Abaye was, אקפי נחמני, akfei Nachmani, נחמני
Nachmani is אביי's Abaye name, אקפי נחמני akfei Nachmani challenged me, שמעתתא
ומתניתא, shmaitasa umasneisa, with a both traditional teaching like an Amoraic teaching
and with a ברייתא. Baraisa. דאסיר de'assir to also prove that in
this case this wine that was touched שלא בכוונת ניסוך shelo bekavanat
nisuch is forbidden. Okay, שמעתתא shmaitasa the שמעתא shmaita is דההוא עובדא
דהוה בנהרדעא, dehu uvda dehavah binahardea, a story the following story happened
in נהרדעא Nahardea and ואסר שמואל. va'assar Shmuel. I have a story
just like this, a non-Jew came, touched the wine, was angry, etc.,
it wasn't an intent to do ניסוך, nisuch, okay, whatever it was,
and he still said the wine remained forbidden. בטבריה ואסר רבי יוחנן.
be'Tverya va'assar Rabbi Yochanan. In טבריה Tverya and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
also said it was forbidden. So look, the אמוראים Amoraim are פוסק
pasking in cases like this it's forbidden. And forbidden means even in
benefit, right? That's the point, you can't even sell it. Okay, ואמרי
ליה, va'amri lei, and I said back to them to defend the
my position, oh no, there they only forbade it, it's not really
forbidden. The reason they forbade that wine when it was touched that
way is לפי שאינם בני תורה, lefi she'einam bnei Torah, because in
נהרדעא Nahardea and פומבדיתא Pumbedisa they're not so תורה Torah knowledgeable and
therefore you had to be extra strict so that it wouldn't be
like a slippery slope and if you allow this, you'll come to
allow other things. So you had to just say it's all forbidden,
okay, but technically it really is permissible in that case. ואמר לי,
va'amar li, and he said back to me, אביי Abaye said back
to me. טבריא ונהרדעא אינה בני תורה דמחוזא בני תורה? Tiverya ve-Nahardea
eina benei Torah de-Mechuza benei Torah? What? Oh in טבריא Tiverya and
נהרדעא Nehardea they don’t know תורה? Torah? What you think מחוזא Mechuza
where you live in מחוזא Mechuza they do know תורה Torah better?
Like you know so the population is pretty much the same in
both places. They’re pretty cosmopolitan places. You know, what’s his name, Yaakov
Elman has written a lot about מחוזא Mechuza and the cosmopolitan nature
of מחוזא. Mechuza. They’re not so פרום frum in מחוזא Mechuza either,
רבא. Rava. So even if you’re right that technically it’s okay, or
at least okay in benefit, and they’re just being strict because of
their population, you should be as just as strict anyway. Okay, so
that’s point number one, that clearly שמואל Shmuel and who was the
other one here, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan were strict in this type
of a case, even in benefit. ומתניתא, ve-Masnisa, now here’s the ברייתא
Baraita that shows that I was wrong. אגרדמים, Argadamim, אגרדמים Argadamim רש"י
Rashi says is somebody who is basically a government official whose job
it is to make sure that the merchants are like not overcharging
and using the right weights and selling the right products, have the
right things labeled. So he’s going around testing the wine, like to
make sure that it’s, you know, that they’re doing what they should
be as merchants. תוספות Tosafos says that it’s a Greek word that
means just that. Okay, there you go. אגרדמים עובד כוכבים מן היהודי
שקידח במינקת, Argadamim oved kochavim min ha-yehud she-kidech be-mineket, he basically made
a hole in a tube, like a straw, okay, והלה ve-hala and
he sucked up some wine, או שטעם מן הכוס o she-ta’am min
ha-kos or he tasted a little bit of wine like making sure,
you know, like that what you’re selling as Bordeaux of 76 is
really, you know, that quality wine or whatever it might be. והחזירו
לחבית ve-hechziro la-chavit and after he tasted a little, he poured the
rest back into the barrel. Okay, now that is considered to be
similar because what we’re talking about is there is obviously כוונה kavana
but no כוונת ניסוך. kavanat nisuch. Okay, somehow it’s a context where
it’s clear the touch is for some different purpose. Now, so the
point is normally of course we assume a non-Jew touches it, boom,
it’s סתם יינם. stam yeinam. Standard touch makes it סתם יינם. stam
yeinam. What makes these cases different, the guy is angry and he
says, what do you mean, this is wine, or the contestor comes
to test it, is there’s clearly some other context. Okay, which takes
it out of, we can presume in this case because of some
other context that there’s no כוונת ניסוך. kavanat nisuch. Okay, there’s some
other context. That by the way was different than up here, which
was indirect and no intent to touch. Here there’s no intent for
ניסוך. nisuch. Okay, there is an intent to touch. Okay, so what’s
the story? Okay. So anyway, that seems to be the case here.
זה היה מעשה, ze haya ma'aseh, so that was the story, ואסרו
ve-asru and they said it was forbidden. So look, here’s this case,
אביי Abaye says to רבא, Rava, the wine is forbidden. Okay, so
you see you’re wrong. מאי לאו בהנאה, mai lav be-hana'ah, doesn’t that
mean that it’s forbidden and you can’t get benefit? Meaning maybe you’re
right, you could like sell it and not charge for the, like
רב הונא Rav Huna said, sell the whole barrel minus the value
of that wine, but you can’t charge for that wine, okay, that
wine is forbidden in benefit. לא, בשתייה, lo, bi-shtiyah, so רבא Rava
tried to push back. No, no, no, it just meant don’t drink
it, but you can get הנאה hana'ah from it. So אביי Abaye
said, I’m not buying that. אי הכי ליתני ימכר, iy hachi lisney
yimacher, then the, that ברייתא Baraita should have said in that case
where he drank a little and put it back, it should have
said, you have to sell the barrel, right? If you really were
allowed to get benefit, just say, sell the barrel. It didn’t say
sell the barrel, it said it’s forbidden, which means it’s flat out
forbidden. Again, you could still sell it minus the value of that
wine, okay, but that wine is totally forbidden. Okay, if that wine
was permissible in benefit, it would have said ימכר. yimacher. And how
do I know that? כי דקתני סיפא, ki de-katani seifa, because the
end of the ברייתא Baraita teaches a case that actually concludes not
it’s forbidden, but concludes with the words, sell it. Okay, here’s the
end of it. חרם עובד כוכבים, cherem oved kochavim, a non-Jewish חרם,
charam, which רש"י Rashi basically says means like some, I don’t know,
angry impetuous person, okay, שהושיט ידו לחבית וכסבור של שמן היא ונמצאת
של יין, she-hoshit yado la-chavit ve-kasavar she-shemen hi ve-nimtsas yayin, he sticks
his hand in a barrel and he thinks it’s going to be
oil. He doesn’t ask the store owner, hey what is this or
whatever, he says, oh look, here’s some oil, let me test it
or something of that nature. Okay, so that’s a case of, this
is now case number four, direct touch plus no כוונה kavana to
touch, meaning to touch wine. Okay, he knows he’s touching, but he
thinks he’s touching oil. Okay, you got that? And so this is
the first case where it said אסור. assur. Here we’re going to
conclude no הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, that’s obviously where that whole discussion is
leading with רבא, Rava, everybody is disagreeing with him, says you can’t
get benefit. And here we’re going to say don’t drink. Plus yes
הנאה hana'ah. *hana'ah*. Plus yes הנאה *hana'ah*. Okay? So this is רבא
Rava *Rava*'s case where everybody is arguing him that he's wrong, as
long as he intended to touch even if there was clearly some
other context of touch, if it's direct touch, don't get benefit. But
if he didn't intend to touch wine and then okay, don't drink
it but yes you can get benefit. All right, so פתח והוציא
ידו לחבית וכסבור שהיא של שמן והיא נמצאת יין *patach vehotzi yado
lachavit vechasavur shehi shel shemen vehi nimtzeit yayin*, זה היה מעשה *zeh
hayah ma'aseh* ואמרו ימכר *ve'amru yimacher*, sell it, which means don't drink
it but yes get benefit. תיובתא דרבא תיובתא *tiyuvta deRava tiyuvta*, that
is it, that's the complete contradiction of רבא Rava *Rava*. Okay, so
now what we've got here is okay and maybe here let's try
to make a better chart, so you see how we've got these
sort of three conclusions. Rabbi, why case number three wouldn't תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* have some solution because this saying that he'd have to throw
out anything that this inspector came to check.
No, he wouldn't have to throw it out, he could sell the
whole barrel minus the benefit. No, you can't get benefit from the
wine that was touched. You can sell the whole barrel and not
charge for that amount of wine. Okay? So you don't have to
throw out the whole barrel. Okay?
You got it? Okay. But if he's sticking his hand in the
barrel how do you know what percentage of? Oh, no, so the
last case where he sticks his hand in where he wasn't intending
to touch wine, you can get benefit.
In the case of the inspector, okay, if he were to actually
stick his hand in the whole barrel you'd have a problem, but
that wasn't the case. The case was he drank a little bit
of wine and you know then the amount that he touched fell
back in or something, a small he touched a small amount then
it fell back in. So in that case you can sell the
whole barrel minus the amount that he touched. But if he directly
touched the wine that would be a problem. So he scoops it
out with like a scoop. If he scoops it out with a
scoop, drinks it, puts it back, sell the whole thing minus that.
If in his process of scooping it out his hand touched it,
then you got then you got a problem, then you got then
you have to throw it all out. What if the Jew suggested
to the inspector that I do this for you? Sure, why not?
Unless the inspector then spills the rest back. Exactly. Okay, all right.
So he says like this. Now
okay now let's keep on going. Okay תיובתא דרבא תיובתא *tiyuvta deRava
tiyuvta*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. בר ארזא רבי יוסי בן נהוראי הוו
יתבי וקא שתו חמרא *Rabbi Yochanan bar Arza Rabbi Yosi ben Nehorai
hava yatvei veka shatu chamra*. They were sitting and drinking wine ואתא
הוא גברא *ve'ata hu gavra*, so a certain man walked by. אמרו
ליה אשקין *amru lei ashkin*, oh hey would you mind come bringing
us a bottle of wine? We need a refill here. Okay so
they must have been in some context where they figured they could
just ask some random person to come refill their bottle.
Okay so אשקין לבתר דרמא לכסא *ashkin levatar derama lechasa*, after he
poured wine into their glasses this man, איגלאי מלתא דעובד כוכבים הוה
*iglai milta de'oved kochavim havah*, it turned out that person they asked
was a non-Jew. Which by the way just makes it obvious that
in the ancient world they were not always, it wasn't always obvious
from the way people
dressed or appeared whether they were Jewish or non-Jewish. חד אסר אפילו
בהנאה *chad assar afilu behana'ah*, so was like all right that's it
gotta spill out this wine now or you know it's forbidden even
in benefit. וחד שרי אפילו בשתיה beshtiya. *vechad sharei afilu bishtiyah*, says
what are you talking about? We can even drink the wine that
he poured for us. What? How could you drink the wine he
poured for us? So אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי מאן דאסר שפיר
אסר ומאן דשרי שפיר שרי *amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi man de'assar
shapir assar oman desharei shapir sharei*. Each one has a legitimate position.
מאן דאסר *man de'assar*, the one who says it's forbidden, מימר אמר
*meimar amar*, says like this, look. He says like what do we
think this non-Jew was thinking when we asked him to pour the
wine? So the one who said it was forbidden says look, the
non-Jew must have said to himself סלקא דעתך דרבנן כי הני שיכרא
קא שתו *salka datchach derabbanan ki hanei shichra ka shatu*? The non-Jew
must have said look, these are very important Rabbis, so you know
if you're important you don't drink beer, if you're a higher social
status you drink wine. So he realized that we were drinking wine.
אלא ודאי האי חמרא הוא *ela vadai hai chamra hu*, it must
be they're drinking wine. So he knew when we asked him to
come bring over the the jug and pour us, he knew that
he was dealing with wine.
ונסכיה *venaschei*, and therefore he touched wine, okay now it's a question
did he touch it, did he pour it and it's only כחו
*kocho*? We're going to bracket that for a moment. But he knew
he was dealing with wine and therefore a non-Jew dealing with wine,
touching wine, pouring wine or whatever makes it סתם יינם *stam yeinam*.
Now נסכיה *naschei* doesn't literally mean we know he used it for
יין נסך Yayin Nesech, *yayin nesech*, but it just means that in
a standard case where there's a concern where there's a touch we
concern we're concerning ourselves that that might be what it was about.
Okay. Now מאן
דשרי *man desharei*, now the one who said it's permissible, שפיר שרי
*shapir sharei*, there's also a good argument that it's all permissible. Why
is that? מימר אמר *meimar amar*, because he says the opposite point.
What did this non-Jew think? סלקא דעתך דרבנן כי הני חמרא קא
שתו ואמרו לי לדידי אשקין *salka datchach derabbanan ki hanei chamra ka
shatu ve'amru li lidi ashkin*? He said how could it be these
If they were drinking wine, how would these חשוב chashuv rabbis ask
me to pour them wine? The non-Jews knew they weren't supposed to
touch the wine of the rabbis. I don't know if you remember
a long time ago on דף ל, Daf Lamed, it says that
שמואל Shmuel was sitting with a certain non-Jew, and the non-Jew sort
of like pulled his hand back rather than touch the wine. And
שמואל Shmuel said to him, "it's okay, it's all יין מבושל Yayin
Mevushal anyway." I don't know if you remember that story. Anyway, so
non-Jews knew we're not supposed to drink wine that they touch. So
this non-Jew must have said, "hey, if they're asking me to pour
a wine, if they're to pour, it must be we're not dealing
with wine." So אלא
וודאי שכרא הואי, Ella vadai shichra havai, it must be it was
שכרא. shichra. So remember what we said here? If you touched it
without thinking it was wine, okay, now here we said don't drink
it, but you can get הנאה. So we're still going to have
to figure out why they were allowed to drink. Okay, but at
least it seems like we're in case number four, okay? So אלא
וודאי שכרא הואי וקא שתו ולא נסכיה Ella vadai shichra havai v'ka
shatu v'lo naschei and he didn't realize it was wine and therefore
it's not a problem of יין נסך, yayin nesech no way he
could have used it for that. So the גמרא Gemara says, "one
minute, what do you mean he thought it wasn't wine?" והא קא
חזי, V'ha ka chazi, you see when you pour it, it's this
like thick red stuff, it doesn't look exactly like beer. Okay, so
בליליא, B'leilya, ah, it was night. Okay. והא קא מרח, V'ha kamaraach,
he smelled it. סוליי בחדתא, Solai b'chardata, it was new wine and
new wine doesn't really smell, it doesn't give off a smell. One
wonders how these חשוב rabbis drinking new wine. Anyway, והא קא נגע
בה? V'ha ka naga bah? Ah, one minute, but we just said
direct touch plus no כוונה kavana is still אסור assur to drink.
So even if he didn't think it was wine, it should have
still been אסור assur to drink. He touched it. Okay. והא קא
נגע בה בנטלא V'ha ka naga bah b'natla והוי ליה מגע עובד
כוכבים שלא בכוונה ואסור. V'havai lei maga oved kochavim shelo b'kavana v'assur.
He touched it, the נטלא natla by the way is like the
pitcher, not the pitcher, the scooper. By the way, the רשב״א Rashba
says that's why when we make the ברכה bracha when we wash
our hands, we say על נטילת ידיים. Al netilat yadayim. What is
נטילה? netila? The taking of hands. So the רשב״א Rashba actually says
that the word, it comes from נטלא, natla, which is actually the
thing you use to wash the hands,
the laver, the cup, anyway,
anyway, so anyway, so the נטלא natla is the scooper, okay? So
he says, anyway, when he went to scoop it out, his hand
touched it. So the answer is לא צריכא דקא מוריק ארוקי. Lo
tzricha d'ka morik aruki. He didn't directly touch it. You know, it
was in the carafe or whatever it was in, and he never
directly actually touched it, he never scooped it out of the barrel
having his hand touch it, or if he did scoop it out,
it was indirectly through this scooper, okay? And it was just pouring
it. והוה ליה כוחו שלא בכוונה V'havai lei kocho shelo b'kavana וכל
כוחו שלא בכוונה לא גזרו ביה רבנן, V'chol kocho shelo b'kavana lo
gazru bei rabbanan, which is this story up here, which is why
תוספות Tosafot, reinterpreted the לולב Lulav story because this is the conclusion
of this גמרא. Gemara. It wasn't, it wasn't direct and no כוונה
kavana to touch, that would have been don't drink. It was indirect
and no כוונה kavana to touch and that you can even drink.
Okay. You can drink today then if a waiter comes over and
pours out? Very good question. So according to the רמ״א, Rama, the
רמ״א Rama says now again, here was a case where it was
no כוונה, kavana, he didn't think it was wine, he thought it
was oil, right, remember that's the case. Or the touch was completely
incidental, he accidentally, he was coming down with a לולב Lulav and
the לולב Lulav accidentally touched. In our cases, it would have been,
it should be indirect with כוונה kavana of wine, which still would
be אסור assur to drink, he knows it's wine. But there is
a ruling of the רמ״א Rama that basically says that because if
you assume Christians aren't in the category of intent to ניסוך, nesech,
now here we're talking about intent to touch, but anyway, wants to
possibly there is an argument to say that בדיעבד b'di'eved I've written
about this, okay, and people obviously it goes back to תוספות, Tosafot,
you don't want to say this לכתחילה, l'chatchila, but there is that
בדיעבד b'di'eved once the wine was poured, the combination of the fact
that it was indirect and we're dealing with contemporary non-Jews where יין
נסך nesech is not such an issue, whatever, that actually בדיעבד b'di'eved
it would be okay. Certainly what's left in the bottle would be
בדיעבד b'di'eved okay, you know, but anyway, but questions about is it
a case of הפסד, hefsed, not a case of הפסד, hefsed, but
yes, that's exactly the argument that's made. So if I try to
sort of, I don't know, distill some of this, okay, what we
have here is the question about,
I'm still trying to think about how to do this. Direct and
indirect touch, let's see if we can do this. Okay, then here
we have to have
כוונה kavana to touch at all or to touch wine, you know
you're dealing with wine, and
as opposed and here it's כוונת ניסוך, kavanat nisuch, right. So and
then here we have to sort
of put this like four categories, yeah, I need a bigger chart,
but anyway. Hold on. So.
Okay. Okay, so, sorry, this needs to be a bit bigger but
anyway. All right. So, if it is, let's see if we can
do this. Okay, so this would
be yes כוונת kavanat touch, no כוונה, kavana, yes, no. So, if
it is, people start to get what I'm trying to do here,
first okay, if it is direct touch with כוונה kavana to touch
wine, so that's obviously אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah.
If it is direct touch with no כוונה kavana to touch wine,
okay, that was our case about the case about the guy who
stuck his hand in and thought it was oil or whatever, which
is just אסור בשתיה. assur beshtiya. Don't drink it. All right. People
with me here? If it's indirect touch, okay, with no כוונה kavana
to touch, that's מותר muttar completely. Okay, that was the case of
the לולב lulav or that was the case here where the guy
poured the wine, it was indirect and he didn't think it was
wine. That's completely מותר. muttar. This is the case we're dealing with
right here. If it's indirect and you know you're dealing with wine,
okay, that's the classic case of the non-Jew nowadays pouring a bottle
of wine, right, yes, that was your case David, right? So that
would be presumably אסור בשתיה. assur beshtiya. Okay, so basically, if you
have both things bad, it's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Okay, if you
have both things good, indirect and no כוונה kavana to touch wine,
it's מותר muttar completely, and if you have one or the other,
it's just אסור assur to be to drink. People getting this? Yep,
yep. Okay, let's look at this part, okay, no כוונת ניסוך. kavanat
nisuch. So,
direct touch and כוונת ניסוך, kavanat nisuch, guess what? Okay, that's אסור
בהנאה. assur behana'ah. Yeah, okay.
I mean, okay, we need here's a bigger line here to divide
these two things. Okay, okay. All right, so, direct touch and no
כוונת ניסוך, kavanat nisuch, that was the case about the רבא's case
about the guy got mad, right? And said oh, what are you
talking about or whatever, like or the inspector, right, remember that? Yes,
that case we just did with the inspector and the guy who
got mad, okay, and there actually we concluded that actually that is
אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. I'm sorry, as long you just because you
didn't have כוונת ניסוך kavanat nisuch it doesn't matter, you had כוונה
kavana to touch the wine, so this is going to be אסור
בהנאה. assur behana'ah. That was the debate of רבא so we included
just decided here, we just make it, it doesn't matter yes or
no, both of those cases are אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. How about
indirect touch and no כוונת ניסוך? kavanat nisuch? We haven't dealt with
that. So we don't exactly know what the answer here is. Indirect
touch and you are intending to touch it but you're not intending
for for ניסוך. nisuch. It would certainly be אסור בשתיה, assur beshtiya,
well, certainly in this case, כוונת ניסוך kavanat nisuch and indirect, מאי
שנא mai shna from the case above, right? Yes, here your כוונה
kavana was to touch wine
and it was indirect,
right. כוונת ניסוך kavanat nisuch includes כוונה kavana to touch. Right, right.
The question is, yeah, I mean presumably when we say כוונת, kavanat,
right, so presumably it's minimally אסור, assur, yeah, בשתיה. If we're assuming
the pos... yeah, presumably it's אסור בשתיה. assur beshtiya. The question is,
is no כוונת ניסוך kavanat nisuch here when it's no כוונה kavana
to touch,
presumably, I don't know for sure, but presumably this whole category remains
like אסור בשתיה, assur beshtiya, okay, but anyway. I so have to
think more about the bottom part of this, okay, but anyway. All
right, so that's pretty much of a summary. Can you take a
picture of that when you're done? Yeah, pretty that's pretty much of
a summary of what we did. I'll have to double check it,
but anyway. All right, let's just finish the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. כל
דלא בכוונה לא גזרו
ביה רבנן. Kol de-lo bekavana lo gozru beh rabbanan. בעי מיניה רב
אסי מרבי יוחנן. Ba'ei minei Rav Assi me-Rabbi Yochanan. רב אסי Rav
Assi asked רבי יוחנן. יין שמסכו עבודת כוכבים מהו? Yayin she-mascho avodat
kochavim mahu? Let's say the wine was mixed, the non-Jew didn't touch
the wine, he just added the water, what would be the story?
Would that be like his energy is in the water, moving the
water, but he never even moved the wine, he just poured the
water in? אמר ליה ואימא מזגו, Amar leh v-eima mazgo, why do
you say מסכו? mascho? The language is מזגו, mazgo, to mix it.
אמר ליה אנא כדכתיב קאמינא, Amar leh ana ki de-chsiv kamina, I'm
quoting a פסוק. pasuk. It says
טבחה טבחה מסכה יינה. Tavcha tivcha mascha yeina. She slaughtered her slaughtering,
she mixed the wine. אמר ליה לשון תורה לעצמה לשון חכמים לעצמה.
Amar leh lashon Torah le-atzmah lashon chachamim le-atzmah. I'm very impressed, but
you know what? We're here in a rabbinic conversation, so use rabbinic
language. The rabbinic language is מזגו. mazgo. Okay, he said fine, thank
you for correcting my grammar. Now, מאי, mai, what's the הלכה? halacha?
So אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said to him, אסור. assur.
It's אסור, assur, why? You didn't even touch the wine, you just
poured water in the wine. משום לך לך אמרינן נזירא סחור סחור
לכרמא לא תקרב *mishum lech lech amrinan nezira sechor sechor l'charma lo
tikrav*. This is basically a safeguard. Go away, go away, we say
to the נזיר *nazir*, don't come close to the vineyard. Okay, so
a נזיר *nazir* and wine, this is also about wine, but it
means it's a safeguard. Technically you're right, it's probably totally permissible, but
as a safeguard we say it's forbidden. Now what does forbidden mean?
Forbidden to drink, forbidden in הנאה *hana'ah*, not clear. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
anyway assumes it means forbidden to drink. Okay, but this is you
didn't even touch the wine, you just added the water. All right.
So now רב ירמיה איקלע לספתא *Rav Yirmeyah ikla
l'Safta*, he came to this place ספתא *Safta*. חזא חמרא דמזגי עובדי
כוכבים ושתיי *chaza chamra d'mazgei ovdei kochavim v'ishtei*. He saw wine that
non-Jews mixed, they added the water to it and the Jews were
drinking it. ושתיי ישראל מיניה *v'ishtei Yisrael minei* ואסר להו *va'asar lehu*,
and he said it's forbidden. משום לך לך אמרינן נזירא סחור סחור
לכרמא לא תקרב *mishum lech lech amrinan nezira sechor sechor l'charma lo
tikrav*. Again, technically it's probably okay, they just poured in the water,
but rabbinically as a safeguard don't drink from it. Minimally don't drink,
maybe even no get הנאה *hana'ah*. איתמר נמי *itmar nami* was also
said, אמר רב יוחנן *amar Rav Yochanan* ואמרי לה אמר רב אסי
אמר רב יוחנן *v'amri lah amar Rav Assi amar Rav Yochanan*, יין
שמזגו עובדי כוכבים אסור assur, *yayin shemazgo ovdei kochavim assur*. If it's
added the water to wine it's forbidden. משום לך לך אמרינן נזירא
סחור סחור לכרמא לא תקרב *mishum lech lech amrinan nezira sechor sechor
l'charma lo tikrav*, fine. ריש לקיש איקלע לבצרה *Resh Lakish ikla l'Botzrah*.
ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* came to this place בצרה *Botzrah*, which sounded
like בצר *Betzer*, which is a place in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*.
חזא ישראל דקאכלי פירי דלא מעשרי *chaza Yisrael d'ka'achlei peirei d'lo ma'asrei*.
He saw Jews that were eating fruit that hadn't taken מעשר *ma'aser*
from it. ואסר להו *va'asar lehu*, and he said no, you're not
allowed to eat this fruit, it's טבל *tevel*. חזא מיא דסגדי להו
עובדי כוכבים *chaza maya d'sagdei lehu ovdei kochavim*. He saw water that
they were bowing down to. ושתו *v'shatu* and then they had no
problem drinking it, וישראל *v'Yisrael*, and the Jews were drinking it. ואסר
להו *va'asar lehu*, he said it's forbidden, it's עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*.
אתא לקמיה דרב יוחנן *ata l'kamei d'Rav Yochanan*. He came to רב
יוחנן *Rav Yochanan*. אמר ליה *amar lei*, רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* said
to him, עד מקטורך עלך *ad miktorach alach*, while your coat is
still on you, don't even take your coat off, don't get comfortable,
turn back around and go back to where you came from. זיל
הדר *zil hadar*, go back and tell them that retract your rulings,
what they did actually was fine. Why? בצר לאו היינו בצרה *Betzer
lav haynu Botzrah*. בצר *Betzer* and בצרה *Botzrah* are different places. בצר
*Betzer* is in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, בצרה *Botzrah* is outside of
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, so תרומות ומעשרות *terumot u'ma'asrot* are not a
problem. This huge תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* of בצר *Betzer* that goes all
the way to the next עמוד *amud* is a whole long discussion
of do תרומות ומעשרות *terumot u'ma'asrot* apply outside of ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael*. From this itself it sounds like they do not, but there's
plenty of גמרות *Gemaras* that sound like they do apply outside of
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. תוספות *Tosafot* has two answers why we don't
practice תרומות ומעשרות *terumot u'ma'asrot* outside of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. One
is because they lived in a feudal society, so technically the land
wasn't theirs. That's an interesting answer, it all belonged to the non-Jews.
The other answer תוספות *Tosafot* says, which is the more universally accepted
one, is that when the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* talks about תרומות ומעשרות
*terumot u'ma'asrot* applying outside of the land of Israel, it means in
the immediate adjoining areas, like you know like Syria and Transjordan, whatever.
When you get seriously far away, it never applied at all, okay?
Still doesn't exactly apply to this בצר *Betzer* and בצרה *Botzrah*, because
those are both very contingent. Why wouldn't it apply further away? Because
it wasn't like it's all an extension of the הלכה halacha, *halacha*
of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. You know, fundamentally it only applies in
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. If it applies outside, it's only rabbinic, so
we might apply it to places that are, you know, seen as
an extension of Israel. Okay, so anyway it says like this, ומים
של רבים *u'mayim shel rabbim*. Now how about the water? Aren't they
bowing down to the water? No, מים של רבים אין נאסרין *mayim
shel rabbim ein ne'asarin*. It belongs to the community and therefore, you
know, when they worship stuff that they don't own, obviously you can't
make it forbidden. רב יוחנן לטעמיה *Rav Yochanan l'ta'amei*, רב יוחנן *Rav
Yochanan* goes according to his reasoning, דאמר רב יוחנן משום רבי שמעון
בן יהוצדק *d'amar Rav Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak*, מים של
רבים אין נאסרין *mayim shel rabbim ein ne'asarin*. If it belongs to
the community you can't make it forbidden. The גמרא *Gemara* says one
minute, הא דיחיד נאסרין *ha d'yachid ne'asarin*? Would that mean that if
it's privately owned you can? ותיפוק ליה דהא מחוברים נינהו *v'teipok leh
d'ha mechubarim ninhu*, but it's part of the landscape and we said
you can't make things that are part of the landscape forbidden by
worshipping them. לא צריכא דתלשינהו *lo tzericha d'talshenu*. No, we're talking about
that the water, דתלשינהו גלא *d'talshenu gala*, that the wave like you
know the water it got washed up on the shore, so it's
not basically still part of the river. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara*
says סוף סוף אבני הר שנידלדלו נינהו *sof sof avnei har shenidaldalu
ninhu*. Okay, but even though it's not attached, it still hasn't been
human sort of controlled. It's like a rock from a mountain that
fell off, remember we had that discussion before? So on the one
hand it's not physically attached, but on the other hand it has
not been controlled by a human being yet. And that was a
debate whether you could make that forbidden. גלא *gala*, so תסתיים דרב
יוחנן דאמר אסורין *tistayem d'Rav Yochanan d'amar asurin*? Should we therefore conclude
that רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* says when a part of the physical
landscape comes off, is no longer attached, even if it's not handled
by humans it can be forbidden? So the גמרא *Gemara* says no,
לא צריכא דטפחינהו בידיה *lo tzericha d'tapchenhu b'yadei*. You don't have to
say the wave splashed it, you could say they themselves splashed the
water out of the river out of the well and they as
a human being they drew the water out and then they worshipped
the water and that water would be forbidden. Okay, if it was
privately owned, but he said don't give them a hard time, this
is publicly owned water and therefore it's all okay, go back and
retract it. So that was a nice little break, but the big
point was we have the big discussion about תינוק *tinok* and the
relevance for Christians
nowadays where תוספות *Tosafot* concludes. that if there's direct touch with כוונה
kavanah to touch wine, it's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah even if there's
no כוונות ניסוך, kavanos nissoch, okay, if there's no כוונה kavanah to
touch wine or if it's indirect with, if it's one of the
two it's אסור בשתייה, assur beshtiyah, and if you have two things,
so if you have two things bad, okay, it's going to be
completely אסור, one good and one bad, it's got to be אסור
בשתייה, assur beshtiyah, and two things good, indirect and no כוונה kavanah
even to touch wine, it'll be completely מותר, mutar, okay? So that's
the important sort of conclusion. I want to say one last thing
although we're over, but just look at this תוספות, כתב הרי, Kasav
HaRi, okay, like on the נח עמוד ב, nun chet amud beis,
under כי דכתיב, ki dechsiv, it's not even going on a גמרא,
he's just telling you a פסק. psak.
כתב הרי, Kasav HaRi, I think that's
אור זרוע, Or Zarua, בזמן הזה עובדי כוכבים שכשך ביינו של ישראל
מותר למכרו לעובדי כוכבים. Bizman hazeh ovdei kochavim shichshach beyeino shel Yisrael
mutar lemachro le'ovdei kochavim. If a non-Jew came and moved his hand
around, you can sell it. Why? That's direct touch, okay? דלא בקי
בשכשך כדפרישית לעיל אבל בשתייה אסור ודווקא שלא נתכוין ליגע כדי להכעיס
לישראל ולהפסידו. Delo baki beshichshach kefereishis le'eil aval beshtiyah assur vedavka shelo
niskaven liga kidei lehachis leYisrael ulehafsido. So that he sort of is
saying would be sort of like this. He had, what was it?
He had it was
direct, so question is why is it permissible? Like what's he sort
of why should be, oh, it's direct but it is, it is
כוונה to touch the wine. Like it's not exactly clear, it seems,
anyway, it seems like he's sort of saying like this whole thing
about when he says לא בקי, lo baki, he's going back to
this ruling that nowadays non-Jews really cannot make the wine אסור בהנאה.
assur behana'ah. So even though he directly touched it and he moved
his hand around in it and the whole thing, nowadays our non-Jews
cannot make the wine אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. They're not part of
that whole world of, you know, wine and נסך and the whole
thing. Okay, so that's what he means when he says דלא בקי
בשכשך, delo baki beshichshach, that's presumably what he means. But then he
says, here's the important point: ודווקא שלא נתכוין ליגע כדי להכעיס לישראל.
Vedavka shelo niskaven liga kidei lehachis leYisrael. But all of that is
if he's not doing it in order to, he knows our הלכות,
halachos, and if he's doing it in order to make it forbidden
because he's angry at us, and says ולהפסידו, ulehafsido, אבל חזינן לדעתי
דעובדי כוכבים שנוגע ביינו של ישראל כדי להכעיסו ולהפסידו ההוא שרי אפילו
בשתייה דכי האי גוונא לא גזרו רבנן. Aval chazinan leda'ati de'ovdei kochavim
shenoge'a beyeino shel Yisrael kidei lehachiso ulehafsido hahu shari afilu beshtiyah dechi
hai gavna lo gazru rabbanan. Okay, if he's doing it in intent
to make it forbidden, he doesn't do anything to it. It's even
permissible to drink. Okay, so תוספות sounds like a פסק psak you
needed to do because you didn't want to have this whole opening
that a non-Jew could intentionally come and make all of our wine
forbidden. So you had to פסקן pasken that in that case that
was never included in the גזירה gezeirah and it's מותר mutar even
to drink. Okay, and then he says like this, da da da,
and if you take a look two lines before the next תוספות,
right above the word עד מקטורחא, ad makturcha, he says like this:
וכן כתב בתשובה פעם אחת היה בור של ישראל מלא יין ובא
אנס אחד ונתן ידו לתוכו להכעיס. Vechen kasav bitshuvah pa'am achas hayah
bor shel Yisrael malei yayin uva anas echad venasan yado letocho lehachis.
Okay, and he so, and a powerful non-Jew came and put his
hand into make it forbidden. והיה שם זקן אחד ירא שמים, Vehayah
sham zaken echad yere shamayim, there was one very, an elder there
who was great, who was a very pious. סופו נהרג על קידוש
השם בעוונותינו הרבים. Sofo neherag al kiddush hashem ba'avonoseinu harabbim. It's very,
so fascinating, right, the very sort of real world details we're getting
here. In the end he was martyred, presumably later like, you know,
during one of the crusades he martyred himself. That's evidence of how
how pious this person was.
ושמענו, Ushamanu, and what he did at that time when this non-Jew
came to "Ha! I'm making it all forbidden, I'm sticking my hand
in it," שלקח מן היין בכלי ושתה ממנו בפני האילן. Shelakach min
hayayin בכלי veshashah mimenu bifnei ha'ilan. He said, "Yeah, that's what you
think," and this pious Jew came and drank straight from the wine
that the non-Jew had stuck his hand in to prove to him
you can't make our wine
forbidden. כדי שלא יהא רגיל לעשות כן לישראל אחר עד כאן לשונו.
Kidei shelo yehei ragil la'asos ken leYisrael acher ad kan leshono. So
you might have said that doesn't prove that's the הלכה, halacha. that
was just like a necessary policy to stop it from happening again,
to show him at that moment that it's you're not going to
do anything, but anyway that becomes an interesting, just shows you the
world they're living in, that if it's done with that intent, you're
gonna, you're not even going to make it forbidden. But the key
really winds up being, you know, this part of it, which is
two good things it's totally מותר, mutar, okay, one good, one bad
it's אסור בשתייה, assur beshtiyah, both of them are bad it's אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, but once you apply to our non-Jews nowadays, you
know, this point, then nothing ever really becomes אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah.
Okay, we'll end with that. Now you know everything you needed to
know about the הלכה.